Guide to the J.J. Donovan Papers 1872-1941
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
J.J. Donovan Papers
1872-1941
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Donovan, J. J. -- (John Joseph), -- 1858-1937.; Donovan, Clara, -- 1858-1936 -- Correspondence.; Bennett, Nelson -- Correspondence.; Donovan family -- Archives.; Donovan family -- Correspondence.
XOE_CPNWS0348
20 linear ft.
The collection consists of the personal, family and business papers of early-Bellingham developer and civic leader John Joseph (J.J.) Donovan.
John Joseph (J.J.) Donovan (1858-1937) was born in Rumney, New Hampshire to Patrick and Julia (O'Sullivan) Donovan on September 8, 1858. J.J. attended Plymouth Normal School where he met his future wife, Clara Nichols (1858-1936). Both J.J. and Clara graduated in 1877 and passed their teaching examinations, although neither would continue teaching for very long. Clara became a piano teacher and J.J. enrolled in Worcester Polytechnic Institute's civil engineering program, where he graduated as Valedictorian in 1882.
Shortly after graduating, J.J. was hired by the Northern Pacific Railway Company to survey, plan and eventually supervise the building of roadbeds and bridges during construction of Northern Pacific's transcontinental system. This appointment brought him west to Montana and eventually Washington State, where he worked on a number of Northern Pacific's Cascade Division projects for the next several years. By the late-1880s, J.J.'s engineering achievements were well known and his services were sought by various commercial interests then being developed on Bellingham Bay in Washington State. These attracted J.J. and Clara to Western Washington, and they arrived in Fairhaven (which later became part of Bellingham) in 1888.
J.J. quickly became involved in real estate and other business ventures, often in partnership with other well-known area businessmen including Nelson Bennett, C.X. Larrabee, Julius H. Bloedel, and Peter Larson. Over the course of his career, J.J. served as Chief Engineer for the Fairhaven Land Company, the Skagit Coal & Transportation Company, the Fairhaven & Southern Railway Company, the Tideland Appraisers, the Blue Canyon Coal Mining Company, the Bellingham Bay & Eastern Railway Company, and the Bellingham Bay & British Columbia Railway Company. He later gave his attention to the lumber business, building and managing the Lake Whatcom Logging Company, Larson Lumber Company, and Bloedel-Donovan Lumber Mills.
J.J. was active in civic life, serving on the Fairhaven City Council, the Board of Trustees of the Whatcom Normal School (now Western Washington University), and sitting as president of several other cultural and professional associations. He helped raise funds for the construction of St. Joseph's Hospital and Assumption Catholic Church, and publicly spoke out against the Ku Klux Klan. J.J. and Clara built a home on McKenzie Avenue in Fairhaven and had three children: Helen Donovan Craven, J.N. "Jack" Donovan, and Philip Donovan.
The J.J. Donovan Papers consist of Correspondence (1874-1942); Journals, Diaries, and Notebooks (1872-1933); School and College Materials (1875-1982); Business and Financial Records (1873-1942); Writings and Speeches (1882-1924); Images and Film (1920s); Ephemera and Artifacts (1882-1923); and Published Materials (1894-1937).
Correspondence (1874-1942) includes letters between J.J. Donovan and family members, including Clara (Nichols) Donovan, children Helen and John Donovan, and J.J.'s siblings. There is also correspondence that was separated and organized topically by local historians Brian Griffin and Gayle Helgoe, prior to the transfer of records to archival custody. In addition to letters, some of these files may also include photographs, newspapers clippings, and manuscript materials.
Journals, Diaries, and Notebooks (1872-1933) include daily private notes written by J.J. as well as accounts from his travel and some of his work. There are also travel diaries by Clara Donovan, and journals and notebooks kept by the Donovan children.
School and College Materials (1875-1982) comprise items created by J.J. during his time as a student, including essays and papers, grade sheets, notebooks, as well as a brief sketch of J.J.'s early life written by former classmate and childhood friend J.Q. Barlow.
Business and Financial Records (1873-1942) include some professional correspondence, banking and cashbooks, bills and receipts, tax and insurance information, stock certificates and reports from J.J.'s commercial interests, as well as materials from trade and industry conferences.
Writings and Speeches (1882-1924) include love poems, children's poetry, J.J.'s public address re: the Ku Klux Klan, and various other speeches.
Images and Film (1920s) are comprised of mostly unidentified negatives and prints of Donovan family members, as well as some images from Whatcom County/Mount Baker wilderness area and various travels. There are also digital copies of three 16mm films documenting family gatherings, and scenes from the Mt. Baker Lodge, Bellingham waterfront, and surrounding area.
The J. J. Donovan Papers are organized according to the following series arrangement:
Series I. Correspondence, 1874-1942
Series II. Journals, Diaries and Notebooks, 1872-1933
Series III. School and College Materials, 1875-1932
Series IV. Business and Financial Records, 1873-1929
Series V. Writings and Speeches, 1882-1924
Series VI. Images and Film, 1920s
Series VII. Ephemera and Artifacts, 1882-1928
Series VIII. Published Materials, 1894-1930
The collection is open to the public.
The bulk of the collection was originally transferred by Brian Griffin in 2013 (with subsequent transfers from the Whatcom Museum), with formal donation made by Al and Kathy Riggs. Additional materials were donated by Lucile Palifka.
Some items have been temporarily separated from the collection and will be re-partriated once additional preservations measures have been taken. Contact repository for details.
Donovan, J. J.--(John Joseph),--1858-1937--Archives.; Donovan, J. J.--(John Joseph),--1858-1937--Correspondence.
Bloedel-Donovan Lumber Mills (Seattle, Wash.); Larson Lumber Company.; Worcester Polytechnic Institute.
Pacific Northwest; Washington (State)
Railroads--Northwest, Pacific--History--Sources.; Businessmen--Washington (State)--Bellingham--History--Sources.; Civic leaders--Washington (State)--Bellingham--History--Sources.; Logging--Washington (State)--History--Sources; Sawmills--Washington (State)--History--Sources
Expeditions and Adventure; Washington (State)
Personal correspondence.; Records (Documents)
- Correspondence, 1874-1942; Series I
  - Personal and Family Correspondence
    - J.J. Donovan and Clara Nichols/Donovan, 1876-1885 (Box C1, Folder 1-6)
    - J.J. Donovan and Clara Nichols/Donovan, 1886-1887 (Box C2, Folder 1-5)
    - J.J. Donovan and Clara Nichols/Donovan, 1887-1888 (Box C3, Folder 1-5)
    - J.J. Donovan and Clara Nichols/Donovan, 1888 (Box C4, Folder 1-6)
    - J.J. Donovan and Clara Nichols/Donovan, 1889-1906 (Box C5, Folder 1-5)
    - J.J. Donovan and Clara Nichols/Donovan, undated (Box C5, Folder 6)
    - J.J. Donovan and Clara Nichols/Donovan to children, 1907-1921 (Box C5, Folder 7)
    - J.J. Donovan and Clara Nichols/Donovan to children, 1922-1933 (Box C6, Folder 1-4)
    - J.J. Donovan and Clara Nichols/Donovan to children, undated (Box C6, Folder 5)
    - J.J. Donovan and siblings, 1876-1881 (Box C6, Folder 6-8)
    - J.J. Donovan and siblings, 1882-1906 (Box C7, Folder 1-6)
    - J.J. Donovan and siblings, 1913-1931 (Box C8, Folder 1)
    - J.J. Donovan and siblings, undated (Box C8, Folder 2)
    - Clara Nichols/Donovan and children, 1901-1913 (Box C8, Folder 3)
    - Clara Nichols/Donovan and children, 1930-1935 (Box C8, Folder 4)
    - John Donovan, 1881-1889 (Box C8, Folder 5)
    - Helen, 1927-1942 (Box C8, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence
    - General, 1852; 1874-1881 (Box C8, Folder 7-9)
    - General, 1882-1887 (Box C9, Folder 1-6)
    - General, 1888-1889 (Box C10, Folder 1-6)
    - General, 1889-1892 (Box C11, Folder 1-6)
    - General, 1893-1901 (Box C12, Folder 1-7)
    - General, 1901-1919 (Box C13, Folder 1-8)
    - General, 1920-1930 (Box C14, Folder 1-7)
    - General, 1931-1941 (Box C15, Folder 1-2)
    - General, undated (Box C15, Folder 3)
    - Telegraph notebook, circa 1906 (Box C15, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence organized by subject
    - Baby Jack's death, 1919 (Box C15, Folder 5)
    - Barlow, Billy, 1883-1924 (Box C15, Folder 6-7)
    - BB BC Railroad, 1901-1904 (Box C15, Folder 8)
    - Bellingham Bay and Eastern RR, 1901-1903 (Box C15, Folder 9)
    - Bellingham Bay Improvement Co., 1902-1924 (Box C15, Folder 10)
    - Bellingham Publishing/Bellingham Herald, 1913 (Box C15, Folder 11)
    - Bellingham School District, 1914-1931 (Box C15, Folder 12)
    - Bennett, Nelson, 1888-1890 (Box C15, Folder 13)
    - Bloedel Donovan Lumber Co., 1914-1931 (Box C15, Folder 14-15)
    - Bloedel Donovan Mill, 1931 (Box C15, Folder 16)
    - Blue Canyon Mine, 1895-1905 (Box C15, Folder 17)
    - Catholic Church, 1891-1929 (Box C16, Folder 1)
    - Chamber of Commerce, 1907-1925 (Box C16, Folder 2)
    - J.J.'s character and generosity, 1923-1930 (Box C16, Folder 3-4)
    - City of Bellingham, 1910 (Box C16, Folder 5)
    - City of Fairhaven, 1891-1897 (Box C16, Folder 6)
    - City of New Whatcom, 1896 (Box C16, Folder 7)
    - Clubs and societies, 1883-1915 (Box C16, Folder 8)
    - Columbia Valley Lumber Co., 1924 (Box C16, Folder 9)
    - Craven, Helen D., 1923-1930 (Box C16, Folder 10-11)
    - Craven, Leslie, 1931 (Box C16, Folder 12)
    - Daily Reveille, 1903 (Box C16, Folder 13)
    - Donovan, Clara Nichols, 1906; 1928 (Box C16, Folder 14)
    - Donovan, Dan, 1895-1926 (Box C16, Folder 15)
    - Donovan, Jack J.N., 1902-1910 (Box C16, Folder 16-17)
    - Donovan, Philip, 1915-1916 (Box C17, Folder 1)
    - Faith/religious matters, 1891; 1916 (Box C17, Folder 2)
    - Fairhaven Land Co., 1891-1898 (Box C17, Folder 3)
    - Fairhaven Real Estate, 1897 (Box C17, Folder 4)
    - Fairhaven and Southern Railway, 1891-1893 (Box C17, Folder 5)
    - Family matters, 1930 (Box C17, Folder 6)
    - First National Bank of Bellingham, 1911 (Box C17, Folder 7)
    - Foreign trade, 1912-1930 (Box C17, Folder 8)
    - Garden St. house, 1912 (Box C17, Folder 9)
    - Good roads, 1921-1926 (Box C17, Folder 10)
    - Great Northern Railway, 1897 (Box C17, Folder 11)
    - Helen, 1895-1924 (Box C17, Folder 12)
    - Helena, Montana (with accompanying notes from donor), 1888 (Box C17, Folder 13)
    - Herbert Hoover, 1928 (Box C17, Folder 14)
    - House on McKenzie, 1893 (Box C17, Folder 15)
    - Immigration, 1930 (Box C17, Folder 16)
    - Irish question, 1920 (Box C17, Folder 17)
    - Knights of Columbus, 1913-1927 (Box C17, Folder 18)
    - Ku Klux Klan, 1923-1924 (Box C17, Folder 19)
    - Lake Whatcom Logging Co., 1911-1913 (Box C17, Folder 20)
    - Larson Lumber Co., 1903-1904 (Box C17, Folder 21)
    - Larson Mill, Larson Lumber Co., 1901-1907 (Box C17, Folder 22)
    - Lumber-Logging Association, 1912-1915 (Box C17, Folder 23)
    - Marsh, George, 1884-1929 (Box C17, Folder 24)
    - Medical records (J.J.'s), 1924-1927 (Box C17, Folder 25)
    - Mining, 1895-1916 (Box C17, Folder 26)
    - Miscellaneous professional correspondence, 1928 (Box C17, Folder 27)
    - Montana investments, 1888 (Box C17, Folder 28)
    - Montana days, 1883 (Box C17, Folder 29)
    - Mt. Baker Lodge, 1929-1931 (Box C17, Folder 30)
    - National Economic League, 1907-1927 (Box C17, Folder 31)
    - New England Club, 1912 (Box C17, Folder 32)
    - New Leopold Hotel, 1929 (Box C17, Folder 33)
    - Normal School, 1909-1931 (Box C18, Folder 1-4)
    - Northern Pacific Railroad, 1883-1890 (Box C18, Folder 5-6)
    - Pacific Highway Association, 1910-1912 (Box C18, Folder 7)
    - Politics, 1895-1924 (Box C18, Folder 8)
    - Railroad history, 1888 (Box C19, Folder 1)
    - Railroads, miscellaneous, 1887; 1909-1929 (Box C19, Folder 2)
    - Railroad to Spokane, 1916-1917 (Box C19, Folder 3)
    - Real estate, 1910 (Box C19, Folder 4)
    - Rotary Club, 1933 (Box C19, Folder 5)
    - Spruce Matter, 1919 (Box C19, Folder 6)
    - St. Joseph's Hospital, 1890-1933 (Box C19, Folder 7)
    - Temperance, 1922; undated (Box C19, Folder 8)
    - Tidelands appraisers, 1892 (Box C19, Folder 9)
    - Trade associations, 1914; 1921 (Box C19, Folder 10)
    - Wahl Department Store (Grand Theater), 1912 (Box C19, Folder 11)
    - Warren, Uncle Tim, 1882-1892 (Box C19, Folder 12-13)
    - Washington State Recognition, 1905-1929 (Box C19, Folder 14)
    - Worcester Polytechnic, 1882-1932 (Box C19, Folder 15)
    - Youngman's Institute, 1895-1902 (Box C19, Folder 16)
- Journal, Diaries and Notebooks, 1872-1933; Series II
  - Diaries, 1872-1879 (Box D1, Folder 1-7)
  - Diaries, 1880-1883 (Box D2, Folder 1-4)
  - Diary: "Private Notes", 1883-1884 (Box D2, Folder 5)
  - Diaries, 1885-1886 (Box D2, Folder 6-7)
  - Diary: "Private Notes", 1886 (Box D2, Folder 8)
  - Diaries, 1887; 1892-1894 (Box D3, Folder 1-4)
  - Diary: "Notes of trip across Washington, Account of State Road Commission, May 1894 and Trip to California, June 1896" (Box D3, Folder 5)
  - Diaries, 1897-1899 (Box D3, Folder 6-8)
  - Diaries, 1900; 1903-1907;; 1909-1910 (Box D4, Folder 1-8)
  - European Trip Travel Diary, 1911 (Box D4, Folder 9)
  - European Trip Expenses Journal, 1911 (Box D5, Folder 1)
  - Diaries, 1913; 1917 (Box D5, Folder 2-3)
  - Diary: Meetings of the Spruce Board and Lumbermen with the Military, 1919 (Box D5, Folder 4)
  - Diary: "Feb-March Hawaiian Trip", 1923 (Box D5, Folder 5)
  - Travel Diaries, 1925; 1929 (Box D5, Folder 6)
  - Diary, 1933 (Box D5, Folder 7-8)
  - Monthly diaries, 1923-1927 (Box D6, Folder 1-10)
  - Monthly diaries, 1928-1932 (Box D7, Folder 1-13)
  - Notebooks, 1881; 1885-1897 (Box D8, Folder 1-11)
  - Notebooks, 1899-1909 (Box D9, Folder 1-10)
  - Notebooks, 1910-1917; undated (Box D10, Folder 1-6)
  - Engagements Book, undated (Box D10, Folder 7)
  - Address Book (notes re: Japan trip and blank notebook), undated (Box D10, Folder 8)
  - Clara Donovan Travel Diaries, undated; 1911;; 1925;; 1929 (Box D11, Folder 1-4)
  - Helen Elizabeth Donovan Diary, 1908-1912 (Box D11, Folder 5)
  - Helen Elizabeth Donovan Travel Diary, 1911 (Box D11, Folder 6)
  - Helen Elizabeth Donovan Diary, 1913 (Box D12, Folder 1)
  - Philip Donovan Notebook, undated (Box D12, Folder 2)
  - Books of quotations (note: "B.G." or "Belonging to Helen Barrett), circa 1889 (Box D12, Folder 3)
  - Quincy railroad notebook (author unknown), undated (Box D12, Folder 4)
- School College Materials, 1875-1982; 1875-1932; Series III
  - Various school papers from time as a student, 1875-1881 (Box S1, Folder 1)
  - Essays and grade sheets from time as a teacher, undated (Box S1, Folder 2)
  - Essays - Dancing, Could the War Have Been Averted, The Influence of Steam, undated (Box S1, Folder 3)
  - Poem: A Summer Sunset, undated (Box S1, Folder 4)
  - Worcester Free Institute Semi-Annual Examination, 1882 (Box S1, Folder 5)
  - The Second Political Triumvirate, 1882 (Box S1, Folder 6)
  - Various school notes, exams, 1875-1877 (Box S1, Folder 7)
  - Chemistry Review, undated (Box S1, Folder 8)
  - Chemistry notebook, 1880 (Box S1, Folder 9)
  - Physics notebook, undated (Box S1, Folder 10)
  - Math notebook, undated (Box S2, Folder 1)
  - German notebook, undated (Box S2, Folder 2)
  - Notebook - "Notes, 1880"; German lessons (Box S2, Folder 3)
  - Transit book, 1878 (Box S2, Folder 4)
  - F.T.U.S.A. newspapers/newsletters, 1876-1878 (Box S2, Folder 5)
  - The F.T.U.S.A. Newspaper, 1878 (Box S2, Folder 6)
  - High school writing books, undated (Box S2, Folder 7)
  - School receipts and report cards, 1875-1882 (Box S2, Folder 8)
  - Citation for honorary degree, 1932 (Box S2, Folder 9)
  - "School Notes", 1878 (Box S2, Folder 10)
  - "Sketches of the early life of J.J. Donovan" by his classmate J.Q. Barlow (with accompanying notes from donor), undated (Box S2, Folder 11)
- Business and Financial Records, 1873-1942; Series IV
  - Professional correspondence, 1892-1919 (Box F1, Folder 1)
  - Report to Nelson Bennett re: the feasibility of building a railroad line from Coal Mines in Township 35, Range 5 to tidewater, 1888 (Box F1, Folder 2)
  - Cash accounts and financial notes, 1888-1909 (Box F1, Folder 3)
  - Banking book, 1912 (Box F1, Folder 4)
  - J.J. Donovan cash book, inlcudes weekly entries, circa 1884-1887 (Box F1, Folder 5)
  - Bellingham Civic League cash book, circa 1921-1929 (Box F1, Folder 6)
  - Nelson Bennett/Fairhaven Southern charge and expense account book, undated (Box F1, Folder 7)
  - Tax and insurance information re: Fairhaven land, 1912 (Box F1, Folder 8)
  - Bloedel-Donovan Logging Mills papers, 1913 (Box F1, Folder 9)
  - Bloedel-Donovan Lumber Mills printed photo journal, 1922 September 16 (Box F1, Folder 10)
  - Bloedel-Donovan stock certificates issued to Helen Donovan Craven, 1942 (Box F1, Folder 11)
  - The Making of One Hundred and Fifty Million Feet of Fir, Cedar and Spruce lumber yearly, by the Bloedel Donovan Lumber, 1913 (Box F1, Folder 12)
  - Pacific Logging Congress, 1914 (Box F1, Folder 13)
  - National Foreign Trade Council Conference, 1917 (Box F1, Folder 14)
  - Cash book, 1876-1880 (Box F1, Folder 15)
  - Bills and receipts, 1873-1914 (Box F1, Folder 16)
  - Business and charitable activities, circa 1910 (Box F1, Folder 17)
- Writings and Speeches, 1882-1924; Series V
  - Love poems to Clara, 1887-1906 (Box W1, Folder 1)
  - Notebook of children's poetry (possibly written by Clara), undated (Box W1, Folder 2)
  - Poetry, 1882-1888 (Box W1, Folder 3)
  - Poetry booklet, undated (Box W1, Folder 4)
  - J.J.'s account of a trip to Asia, undated (Box W1, Folder 5)
  - Notes, undated (Box W1, Folder 6)
  - "The Catholic Citizen" - J.J. Donovan address re: the Ku Klux Klan (KKK), 1924 (Box W1, Folder 7)
  - Speeches, 1882-1924; undated (Box W1, Folder 8-10)
- Images and Film, 1920s; Series VI
  - Photo album: 'The West Indies and Panama" to Julia from John, undated (Box P1, Folder 1)
  - Photo album: 'Snap-Shots of Our Hawaiian Trip' to Sister Margaret from John and Clara, 1923 (Box P1, Folder 2)
  - Family portraits (mostly identified) and scenery shots, undated (Box P1, Folder 3-4)
  - Glass plate negatives and steel printing plates - portraits of J.J. Donovan, undated (Box P2)
  - Photo: "J.J. Donovan 21 years old", undated (Box P3, Folder 1)
  - Print: "Table Mt. Near Mt. Baker Lodge" by Bert Huntoon, undated (Box P3, Folder 2)
  - 7 negatives, undated (Box P3, Folder 3)
  - 6 envelopes full of negatives, undated (Box P3, Folder 4)
  - 1 envelope of negatives, undated (Box P3, Folder 5)
  - 2 envelopes of photos: "Recent Photos of the Children 9/24/24" and "Helen's Children and Mt. Baker 7/21-22", circa 1924 (Box P3, Folder 6)
  - 15 family photos, undated (Box P3, Folder 7)
  - 47 photos, undated (Box P3, Folder 8)
  - 52 photos, undated (Box P3, Folder 9)
  - 95 photos, undated (Box P3, Folder 10)
  - 12 photos, undated (Box P3, Folder 11)
  - 15 prints and 285 negatives, circa 1920s (Box P3, Folder 12-13)
  - 3 photographs, papers re: Donovan dinner, railroad ticket, theater, etc., undated (Box P3, Folder 14)
  - 15 prints and 10 negatives - papers re: South Bellingham Industrial Club, undated (Box P3, Folder 15)
  - Folder of papers: railroads, Bellingham Chamber of Commerce, National Foreign Trade Council Conference, undated (Box P3, Folder 16)
  - 3 mounted portraits, 40 prints and 8 negatives, undated (Box P3, Folder 17)
  - Photo album, undated (Box P3, Folder 18)
  - 45 small prints, undated (Box P3, Folder 19)
  - 17 mounted portraits, 13 prints, undated (Box P3, Folder 20-21)
  - 115 loose and 5 booklets of postcards, undated (Box P3, Folder 22-23)
  - 1 mounted portrait, 1 negative 5 prints, undated (Box P3, Folder 24)
  - Photographic prints - mostly family, unidentified, a small number of Mt. Baker/industry, postcard of Mt. Baker Lodge, some Roth Easter Egg Hunt, undated (Box P4, Folder P4)
  - Photographic prints - these prints, accompanied by notes from notes from Brian Griffin, undated (Box P5, Folder P5)
  - Photographic negatives - include family travel, undated (Box P6, Folder P6)
  - Photographic prints - portraits of family members, scenery photos, and loose pages once part of a photo album, undated (Box P7, Folder P7)
  - Photo album - Victoria, British Columbia, undated (Box P8, Folder 1)
  - Prints and negatives - banks, Tulip Parade, crows and participants at Battersby Park, California and Arizona, house and garden at St. Jo's (birth, John?), undated (Box P8, Folder 2)
  - Prints - Roth Easter Egg Hunt, undated (Box P8, Folder 3)
  - Prints - scenic shots around Chuckanut Drive and Mt. Baker, including several B.W. Huntoon, also Clyde Banks images, Jacobsen image of bear in snow, circa 1920s (Box P8, Folder 4)
  - Prints - family images, Nooksack Falls, Mt. Baker area, Clallam County mining and logging operations, circa 1920s (Box P8, Folder 5)
  - Prints, negatives and tin type - travels (Santa Rosa Elementary), Mt. Baker, Ruby Beach on Olympic Peninsula, Gt. Northern Line (driving Golden Spike?), Japan, China, Mt. Baker Lodge, Mt. Baker, St. Joseph's Hospital, Clallam, Cargo Mill, Tulip Parade, circa 1920s-1930s (Box P9)
  - Family gathering, undated (Item Film 1)
  - Mt. Baker Lodge, Bellingham waterfront, Larrabee Family home, undated (Item Film 2)
  - Children playing, undated (Item Film 3)
- Ephemera and Artifacts, 1882-1923; Series VII
  - Autograph book - "J.J. Donovan", circa 1882-1885 (Box E1, Folder 1)
  - Badge - Fourth National Foreign Trade Delegation, Pittsburgh, 1917 January 25-27 (Box E1, Folder 2)
  - Blank diaries, undated (Box E1, Folder 3)
  - Book plates - Elizabeth Colbourne, 1925 (Box E1, Folder 4)
  - Business/calling cards, undated (Box E1, Folder 5)
  - Children's Christmas books, 1928 (Box E1, Folder 6)
  - Children's locks of hair - Helen (3 years old) and Jack, 1893 (Box E1, Folder 7)
  - Negative album, 1916 (Box E1, Folder 8)
  - Olive tree leaves, undated (Box E1, Folder 9)
  - Piano key letters, undated (Box E1, Folder 10)
  - Railroad passes, undated (Box E1, Folder 11)
  - Rotary pin, undated (Box E1, Folder 12)
  - Wallets and check holders, undated (Box E1, Folder 13)
  - Wallets and identification cards, undated (Box E1, Folder 14)
  - Assorted ephemera, undated (Box E1, Folder 15)
- Published Materials, 1894-1937; Series VIII
  - American Forestry Association Annual Report, 1930 (Box M1, Folder 1)
  - Bellingham Herald's Chronological Anecdotal and Biographical History of Northwestern Washington, 1910 (Box M1, Folder 2)
  - J.J. Donovan's obituary in the Bellingham Herald, 1937 (Box M1, Folder 3)
  - Bibles, undated (Box M1, Folder 4)
  - "Henck's Field Book for Engineers", undated (Box M1, Folder 5)
  - Books, circa 1890-1928 (Box M1, Folder 6)
  - Catalogs, 1901 (Box M1, Folder 7)
  - Declaration of Principles and By-Laws of the Manufacturers' and Employers' Association, 1911 (Box M1, Folder 8)
  - Final Report of the Cascade State Road Commission of the State of Washington, 1894 (Box M1, Folder 9)
  - Forest Club Quarterly (REMOVED), 1925 (Box M1, Folder 10)
  - History of Christ Church, Alexandria, VA, 1926 (Box M1, Folder 11)
  - Instructions for Operating the Kodascope, undated (Box M1, Folder 12)
  - Journal of Military Service Institution (REMOVED), undated (Box M1, Folder 13)
  - Map of Bellingham (C.M. Adams), 1904 (Box M1, Folder 14)
  - The Gilded Age by Mark Twain, circa 1910 (Box M2, Folder 1)
  - McClure's Magazine, 1903 (Box M2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous articles, undated (Box M2, Folder 3)
  - Montana Society of Engineers directory, 1913 (Box M2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box M2, Folder 5)